Preliminary Guide to the Milton Irwin Roemer Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Milton Irwin Roemer Papers
1930-2000
MS 1786
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
118
The papers include correspondence, writings, topical files, and photographs, which document Milton Roemer's career as a health administrator, a professor of public health, and an advocate for national health insurance. The papers also highlight Roemer's work for the World Health Organization and the Saskatchewan Department of Public Health and include material concerning his loyalty case. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Roemer, Milton Irwin, 1916-2001
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Milton Irwin Roemer, 1998. The papers were received following his death in 2001.
Biographical / Historical
Milton Irwin Roemer was born in Patterson, New Jersey and earned his bachelor's degree in public health from the University of Michigan. He also studied sociology at Cornell University and received a medical degree from New York University. Roemer, an advocate for government supported health programs and health maintenance organizations, held positions in health administration with the United States Public Health Service, the World Health Organization, and the Saskatchewan Department of Public Health. He also taught at Yale University and the University of California Los Angeles. Roemer died on January 3, 2001.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence, writings, topical files, and photographs, which document Milton Roemer's career as a health administrator, a professor of public health, and an advocate for national health insurance. The papers also highlight Roemer's work for the World Health Organization and the Saskatchewan Department of Public Health and include material concerning his loyalty case. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Medical policy; Public health; Roemer, Milton Irwin, 1916-2001
- Inventory, 1930s-2000
  Scope and Contents
  The papers are arranged as received. Office files represent those materials maintained by Roemer in his office at the University of California, Los Angeles, while Home files are those found in the Roemer home. Of particular note are the yearly files, which consist of correspondence, writings, and other materials that document the progression of Roemer's work and interests through his entire professional career.
  - Office files
    - American Medical Association - Los Angeles Welfare Planning Council, 1960s-1980s (Box 1)
    - American Orthopsychiatric Association - American Hospital Association, 1960s-1970s (Box 2)
    - Consultations - International Health Jobs, 1960s-1970s (Box 3)
    - Institute of Industrial Relations - New York Academy of Medicine, 1960s-1970s (Box 4)
    - Enrique Rozenblat/Argentina - Stanford Medical School, 1960s-1970s (Box 5)
    - Martin Cherkasy tribute - Dr. Ted Tulchinsky, 1960s-1990s (Box 6)
    - Changing Health Care, Berkeley - Health insurance research questionnaire, 1960s-1980s (Box 7)
    - Research training - consultations, 1960s-1990s (Box 8)
    - Ambulatory Health Services: Organization, Problems and Future Models B Kreick, Mary, 1960s-1990s (Box 9)
    - Health Administration Development Program- Arizona/rural, 1960s-1990s (Box 10)
    - International Health Coordinator - Pitzer College, 1960s-1990s (Box 11)
    - Hemisphere General - Eastern Europe, 1960s-1990s (Box 12)
    - Saskatchewan Utilization data - Prevention in Health Plans, 1950s-1990s (Box 13)
    - Ideal Health Care System - Patient-centered Service (Russell Sage Fellow), 1970s-1990s (Box 14)
    - Australia - Cornell University hospital administration research program, 1950s-1990s (Box 15)
    - Health and Society - Financing and control, National Health Care Programs, Las Vegas, 1950s-1990s (Box 16)
    - Summary of activities - Art Carstens Memorial, 1950s-1980s (Box 17)
    - Health Insurance Plan of Los Angeles (HIPLA) - Sickness, absenteeism and HMOs, 1960s-1980s (Box 18)
    - Health Care Financing Administration - Group practice, 1960s-1980s (Box 19)
    - Financing medical care for the aging - Johnson Foundation, 1960s- 1980s (Box 20)
    - Johnson Foundation (cont'd) - Division of Health Services, 1960s-1990s (Box 21)
    - Division of Health Services (cont'd) - Guyana, 1960s-1980s (Box 22)
    - National Health Insurance/San Diego - Joint Commission on the Accreditation of Hospitals, 1950s-1980s (Box 23)
    - Krieger, James - Office of Technology Assessment, 1970s-1980s (Box 24)
    - Public health Chronic Disease Program - USA Health System, 1950s-1990s (Box 25)
    - Job offers to me - Professional Step VII, 1960s-1990s (Box 26)
    - Organization of Specific Services - National Health Insurance Proposals (1970s-1980s), 1960s-1980s (Box 27)
    - Health Service Coordination in Guatemala - UNDP/WHO/FRG (BMZ) Study on HRD FOR PHC Joint Review, draft 2, 1970s-1980s (Box 28)
    - Medical Care Costs and Services - Public Medical Care Programs, 1960s-1970s (Box 29)
    - Health Insurance Legislation, the World Perspective - National Health Insurance Care Systems (HCOP), 1960s-1990s (Box 30)
    - Cornell HADP - Hospital Utilization Study, 1950s-1990s (Box 31)
    - Health Care recommendations for Belize - PH206 lecture notes, 1960s-1990s (Box 32)
    - Course materials (Box 33–34)
  - Yearly files
    - 1930s, 1942-1946 (Box 35)
    - 1947-1949 (Box 36)
    - 1950-1952 (Box 37)
    - 1953-1955 (Box 38)
    - 1956-1958 (Box 39)
    - 1959 (Box 40)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 41)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 42)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 43)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 44)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 45)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 46)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 47)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 48)
    - 1973-1975 (Box 49)
    - 1976-1978 (Box 50)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 51)
    - 1981-1983 (Box 52)
    - 1984-1986 (Box 53)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 54)
    - 1988-1990 (Box 55)
    - 1991-1993 (Box 56)
    - 1993-1996 (Box 57)
    - 1996/1997-1999 (Box 58)
    - 2000 (Box 59)
  - Home files
    - International conference files, WHO, general files, photographs (Box 60)
    - WHO (Box 61)
    - Barbados, Burma, Czechoslovakia, PAHO, International health, lectures (Box 62)
    - WHO, publications (Box 63)
    - International files, Alaska, Chile, Nicaragua, Norway (Box 64)
    - Misc. (Box 65)
    - International, 1960s: Europe, Germany, Japan (Box 66)
    - Writings and personal activities (Box 67)
    - Writings (Box 68)
    - Misc. (Box 69–70)
    - Physicians Forum, HEW (Box 71)
    - Thailand, Barbados (Box 72)
    - WHO international conference files (Box 73)
    - Cuba (Box 74)
    - Reports and writings (Box 75)
    - Personal, reports, topical files (Box 76)
    - Publications (Box 77)
    - State files (Box 78)
    - Misc. (Box 79)
    - Textbook (Box 80)
    - International health binders, 1970s-1980s (Box 81)
    - Publications (Box 82)
    - Misc. (Box 83)
    - Textbook, writings (Box 84)
    - Misc. (Box 85)
    - WHO: health centers, Guatemala, Saskatchewan (Box 86)
    - Misc. (Box 87–88)
    - Country files (Box 89)
    - Misc. (Box 90)
    - International (Box 91)
    - International and personal (Box 92)
    - WHO: Albania, Hungary, Poland (Box 93)
    - Manuscripts and writings of others (Box 94)
    - Medical care in Latin America (Box 95)
    - Scrapbooks and writings (Box 96)
    - Misc. (Box 97)
    - WHO: Liberia, Latin America, Kuwait, medical care (Box 98)
    - Misc. (Box 99–102)
    - Misc. (but may be from office rather than home) (Box 103)
    - Misc. (Box 104)
    - State Health Insurance Task Force; Personal (including correspondence in an alphabetical run) (Box 105)
    - Courses and conference (Box 106)
    - Health Services in Western Europe tour (1950); writings; Sigerist (Box 107)
    - Scrapbooks (Box 108)
    - Personal (Box 109)
    - Misc. (Box 110–111)
    - Topical files, 1940s and early 1950s (Box 112)
    - Misc. (Box 113–117)
- Additional Material, 1946-1992; Accession 2002-M-013
  - Speech, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Documents secured in the 1980s and 1990s through the Freedom of Information Act regarding the loyalty investigation of Milton Roemer, Circa 1948-1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Sigerist Circle" marked on outside of box. Folders containing more documents concerning loyalty of MIR and FBI files, Circa 1962-1966 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, correspondence re: loyalty case, 1948-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Passport case, 1952-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1948-1992 (Box 1)